[Music]
this fits into a lot of what I've seen
Eric Weinstein talk about as well is
that what we're seeing at the moment is
a kind of a war on heterodox thinkers
that there is some force that the that
fears individuality in some sense I
think that's partly at the root of this
I think that there's some nuance that
needs to be injected into the
conversation what's the difference
between a cult and a religion I think
that the cult is a negative thing I
think religion isn't a negative thing I
don't think that religion itself is
negative and if you look at people who
get into cults and have to go through
certain steps of deprogramming from a
cult there there's certain sorts of ways
that you get sucked into a cult and
certain things that you need to do to
get out of it that are alive and well
and the grievant studies social justice
progressive mindset there's a lot of
like you're praised for certain
characteristics and that make you feel
good but even though you're being
praised for individual characteristics
that's not the same thing your identity
is not necessarily the same thing as
your individual this is such a difficult
thing to pull apart as well because
you're trying to hold it the complexity
of two perspectives like there's there's
a huge reaction to this from the write
for example and so a lot of the reaction
against the social justice groupthink is
easily characterized by people as well
this is just coming from the right but I
think the complexity that has to be held
is these are good values inclusivity is
a good value treating people with
respect is a good value yes but if you
make these your primary axioms then they
tend to lead to madness if you make
inclusivity and diversity your primary
axioms rather than the dignity of the
individual for example rather than
self-realization rather than free speech
then you're in danger of like if you
make care rather than truth your
fundamental Val
then you're in very dangerous waters
very very quickly because by definition
you are going to then have to stop
certain people speaking if you think
that what they're saying is not is in
danger of offending others for example
it's about and that's where it maps on
to the religious mindset really really
clearly it's like your religious
perspective is what are you making your
primary Aksum is what are you making
your primary values
yeah and that's that's a very delicate
conversation to be had because it's very
easy to say this whole social justice
world is a cult and we've got a we've
got to fight back against it and it's
really it's it's in danger becoming a
new religion but to be able to hold the
complexity of saying we're not saying
your values are wrong we're saying that
taken to an extreme they become wrong
yeah is it like it's it's almost like
threading and I have a needle to make
that to make that conversation or make
those points in a way that doesn't that
allows people to hear them if they're
already minded to go along with this
sort of very black and white narrative
of goodies versus baddies and yeah you
see what I mean it's almost like you
know that that first scene and Indiana
Jones the first one Raiders of the Lost
Ark where he goes into the temple and he
swaps out that gold bag with this statue
I don't want to get to Peter Sounion but
what happens is there's this swapping
out of the ideology with the individual
where the individuals taken out and
what's replaced as the ideology so any
criticism of the ideology feels like a
personal attack and that doesn't
necessarily have to be tied into the
care principle the care harm principle I
think that that can happen anywhere any
ideology any religion taken in to that
extreme where it's an imposition rather
than a journey of self-discovery it's a
communal rite of passage into a
unification it has the capacity to stir
up a lot of defensiveness whenever
somebody criticizes that
you
[Music]